Inventory of the Ernest M. Allison papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Inventory of the Ernest M. Allison papers
1918-2005
2015C19
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box, 1 oversize box (3.4 linear feet)
Diaries, flight logs, correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia of the American aviator relating to commercial aviation in the United States and China before World War II. Includes other family papers and collected material on aviation history.
Allison, Ernest M., 1894-1976.
Access
The collection is open for research. The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
An American aviator, Allison was active in the early days of American aviation, where he was one of the first to fly routes with the US Air Mail service, from 1918 to 1927. Allison moved to China in 1929 to serve the China National Aviation Corporation (CNAC), where he flew mail routes, helped establish and expand the airfield at Shanghai, and oversaw the expansion of CNAC into a commercial passenger line under Pan-American Airways, eventually serving as a vice president of CNAC. He flew important missions, including delivering supplies, flying Soong May-Ling (Madame Chiang Kai-Shek) into Shanghai, and flying Chiang Kai-Shek and Soong May-Ling back to Xi'an after the Xi'an Incident of 1936. Allison was well acquainted with important figures in aviation such as Charles Lindbergh, Claire Lee Channault, Clement M. Keys, William Langhorne Bond, and Harold M. Bixby. Allison returned to the United States after the Communist victory in China and worked in aviation in various capacities, including for Boeing in Seattle.
Scope and Contents of Collection
The collection includes diaries, flight logs, correspondence, books, periodicals, bulletins, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia relating to commercial aviation in the United States and China before World War II. Specifically, the development of the Air Mail Service of the United States Postal Service, and the development of the China National Aviation Company (CNAC) and the services that it provided, notably air mail and later passenger transportation. Includes other family papers and collected material on aviation history, including the autobiography of aviator R. C. "Tex" Marshall, and interviews with former CNAC employees such as Harold Chin, Frieda Chen, Moon Chin, Wong Tsu, and Fred Y. T. Chin. Contains research correspondence with Dick Rossi, James McDivitt, David Feng and personal correspondence with Harold Bixby, William Langhorne Bond, Claire Lee Chennault, Royal Leonard, K. I. Nieh, and H. S. "Newsreel" Wong.
China National Aviation Corporation.; Aeronautics--China.; Aeronautics--United States.
- Career file, 1932-2005
  Scope and Contents
  Contains flight logs, journal, commendations, speech notes, and other materials
  - Interview Notes, 1937-1998
    - Harold Chin, China National Aviation Company (CNAC) Pilot, 1937 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Frieda Chen, CNAC secretary, August 25, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Fred Y. T. Chin, CNAC copilot, 1998 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Nancy Wright to/from William Longhorne Bond, 1988 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Moon Chin, CNAC pilot and captain, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - CNAC Monthly Bulletin, May - September, 1948 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Contains original editions of the bulletin.
  - Pan American Airways, Inc., 1932-1949 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Raw notes about involvement with CNAC.
  - Biography of Wong Tsu (CNAC Chief Engineer 1928-1949) from Museum of Flight in Seattle, Washington, 2005 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - The China Memoirs of Charles S. "Chilie" Vaughn, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Flying Autobiography of R.C. "Tex" Marshall, June 1970 (Box-folder 1: 10-12)
  - "Over the Hump: Pioneering China's Air Routes," by Nancy Allison Wright. Aviation History Magazine, November 1998 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Aviation Articles, 1996-2002 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    Contains articles titled, "America's First Coat-to-Coast Mail Run," "Allie's Choice," and "China's Aviation Pioneer, CNAC, Spreading its Wings."
- Correspondence file, 1926-2012
  - History of CNAC and aviation in China, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Consists of nine DVDs.
  - "Dragon Wings: The Story of the China National Aviation Corporation" and "Saga of CNAC #53" (from CNA Captain Fletcher Hanks), undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
    Consists of two DVDs regarding CNAC history.
  - "On the Trail of the Air Mail", by Lieutenant J. Parker Van Zandt, US Army Air Service. The National Geographic Magazine, January 1926 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - "Yankee on the Yangtze", by Nancy Allison Wright. Aviation Quarterly, 1980 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - "Adventurous Travellers - First in the Skies of China,", 2012 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    Booklet from the Rosamonde Aviation Lounge at The Peninsula Hotel in Shanghai.
  - Flight In the China Air Space 1910-1950, by Malcolm Rosholt, 1984 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Saga of the US Air Mail Service First Edition, Air Mail Pioneers, Inc., 1962 (Box-folder 2: 7-8)
  - Correspondence regarding CNAC from Nancy Allison Wright, 1998 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Interview with Dick Rossi, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Research Correspondence, Charles Euripideas, 1999 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Research Correspondence, David Feng, 1998 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Research Correspondence, James McDivitt, 1948, 1995 (Box-folder 2: 13)
- Books regarding the history of CNAC, 1938
  - Wings Over Asia: A Brief History of China National Aviation Corporation, undated (Box 3)
  - Top Side Ricksha, by Harold M. Bixby, 1938 (Box 3)
    Independently written and bound manuscript.
- Writings, Personal Effects, and Correspondence, 1918-1973
  - Certificates and commendations, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Pilot's Book, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Flight Log, 1939-1944 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Speaking Notes, "Industrialization of China,", 1950 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Business and Membership Cards, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Personal Journal of Ernest Allison, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Writings, 1931-1938 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    Includes Allison's general account of time spent in China, and a story from 1938 titled, "All Asleep But Me," about a flight from Chungking to Changsha.
  - "Landing In a Walled City,", 1962 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Operations Report 1947 - Pan American, January 1948 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - The "All Thru" Flying System of Flying Instruction at Brooks Field, booklet, undated (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1976
    - H. M. Bixby, 1934-1970 (Box-folder 4: 11-13)
    - William Langhorne Bond, 1932-1976 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - H. L. Chen, 1941 (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - Claire Lee Chennault, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 4: 16)
    - H. H. Kung, 1939 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - Royal Leonard, 1939 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - Loy Locke, 1950 (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - Grover Loening, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 4: 20)
    - K. I. Nieh, 1941 (Box-folder 4: 21)
    - Quentin Roosevelt, 1948 (Box-folder 4: 22)
    - T. V. Soong, 1939 (Box-folder 4: 23)
    - Hsien-ling Tseng (Ceng Xianling), 1941-1942 (Box-folder 4: 24)
    - H. D. Walsh, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 25)
    - "Newsreel" Wong, 1941 (Box-folder 4: 26)
- Photographs, 1921-1949
  - Allison, undated, 1921 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
  - Boeing B-20 and B-29 airplanes, Wichita, Kansas, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Boeing 40-A, 1927 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - China, 1929 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - China Clipper, 1934-1937 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - CNAC I, Beijing aerial photos, photo of Longhua (Lunghwa) Pagoda, 1930 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - CNAC II, undated (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - CNAC III, circa 1948 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - CNAC, C-46, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - CNAC, Hong Kong, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    Pictured with William Langhorne Bond, Max Polin, James McDivitt, Hugh Chen, P. Ling, S. T. C. Kao, Q. Rossevelt, Colonel C. Y. Liu, and Colonel C. H. Wang.
  - CNAC, Sikorsky, undated (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - CNAC in Shanghai, Nanjing, Chengdu, 1929-1934 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Ernest Allison with Boeing B29, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Flossie Allison, 1928-1949 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Flooding in Wuhan, 1934 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - "Nidaros,", 1935 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - "Newsreel" Wong, 1929 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Stinson-Detroiter, 1949 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 5: 20-22)
- Florence Allison, 1935-1949
  - Notebook (Box-folder 5: 23)
    Notebook detailing members and associates of the Allison family, and personal information about them.
  - Diary I, 1935, 1947, 1949 (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - Diary II, 1936 (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - Diary III, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - Diary IV, 1942 (Box-folder 5: 27)
- Printed Matter and Maps, 1933-1937
  - Sian: A Coup D'Etat, by Mayling Soong Chiang (Madame Chiang Kai-Shek), and A Fortnight in Sian: Extracts from a Diary, by Chiang Kai-Shek. Copy signed by Mayling Soong Chiang., 1937 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Journal of the West China Border Research Society, Volume VI, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - The Climate of China and The Adjoining Seas, by Father E. Gherzi, S.J. Director, Met. Seismic Observatory for CNAC, undated (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - "China's Children: The Season's Greetings", booklet published by the Publicity Committee, United Church of Canada, West China Mission, undated (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - "'Two Kingdoms' (or the Philosophy of Finance): A Fable for Grown Up People," by "Ivangels,", 1935 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Maps of Shanghai, undated (Box-folder 6: 6)
- Martini Shaker, undated (Box 7)
  Silver martini shaker with relief of a dragon. Gift to Ernest M. Allison from Generalissimo and Madame Chiang Kai-Shek.
- Oversize Material, 1923-1968 (Box 8)
  Hardbound copy of The Saturday Evening Post, October 30th, 1937.
  A 1923 glass plaque commemorating US Air Mail Service Pilots ) from the Detroit Aviation Society.
  A 1931 framed photograph of Ernest M. Allison's sailboat, the "Nidaros."
  War memorial medal given by China National Air Corporation (CNAC) to Ernest M. Allison.
  Plaque commemorating Ernest M. Allison for the 1918 to 1927 Air Mail Service. Awarded in 1968.